Alright. בוקר טוב, Boker tov, apologies about the video.
We are in the exciting עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, מסכת עבודה זרה
Masechet Avodah Zarah at the top of דף כ"ט daf chaf-tet
and we're starting right in the first line. We're continuing our exploration
of rabbinic, mishnaic medicine, some of it a little eerie what we
humanity used to do with our health and some of it very
fascinating.
We're in the middle of the first line. חלא לסיבורי ומוניני לתעניתא.
Chala lesiborei umoninei leta'anita.
Vinegar is good if you're, it's good for one to consume after
bloodletting and small fish is good for one after they've been fasting.
וחילופא סכנתא. Vecheilufa sakanta.
If we do it backwards, fish is for the הקזת דם, hakazat
dam, we'll see in the minute there's going to be instructions on
how to eat fishes with the הקזת דם, hakazat dam, with the
סיבורי, siborei, and vinegar for the fast, that's danger. תחלי וסיבורא סכנתא,
Tachlei vesibura sakanta, אישתא וסיבורא סכנתא, ishta vesibura sakanta, כאב עינא וסיבורא
סכנתא. ke'ev eina vesibura sakanta. So I'm impressed that we're noticing that
bloodletting with almost anything is dangerous.
And the first thing is cress, right, as a plant.
The second one is fever. The third one is eye pain, pain
of the eye, כאב עינא. ke'ev eina.
Okay. Now we have instructions of how to eat fish with the
bloodlet.
שני לדג דם, Sheini ledag dam, שני לדם דג, sheini ledam dag,
שלישי לא סכנתא. Shlishi lo sakanta. So if we eat
on the second day after eating fish, one can let blood and
on the second day after letting blood, one may eat fish. But
on the third day, that's already considering that we're posing a danger.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, המקיז דם לא יאכל חגב"ש. hamakiz dam lo
yochal chagvash. What's חגב"ש? chagvash? It's like army language, we're making acronyms
of things we have to remember. חגב"ש chagvash is חלב, גבינה, בצלים,
שחלים. chalav, gevina, betzalim, shchalim. So here's the גמרא Gemara says, לא
חלב ולא גבינה ולא בצלים ולא שחלים. lo chalav velo gevina velo
betzalim velo shchalim.
The one who is letting blood should not eat milk, cheese, onions,
or cress.
אם אכל, Im achal, which I really love the גמרא Gemara for
this. First it says do not do this and immediately the next
sentence says but then again if he did it, because clearly if
we say don't do it then one will do it. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, נייתי רביעתא דחלא ורביעתא דחמרא ונערבבינהו בהדי הדדי ונישתי. naiti
revi'ata dechala, revi'ata dechamra, venearbevinhu behadi hadadei venishti.
So if somebody did eat this חגב"ש chagvash mixture, then the
cure to it, take a quarter of a log of vinegar and
a quarter wine, mix it with each other and drink. וכי מפנה
לא מפנה אלא למזרחה של עיר משום דקשי ריחא. Vechi mefane, lo
mefane ela lemizrachah shel ir mishum dekashi reicha.
If one goes to the bathroom, it sounds like a number two
bathroom, one should not go
unless one goes on the eastern side of the city because the
smell is very intense and spreads in the city. Really? Yes, בוקר
טוב. Boker tov.
Might this be situational because closer to the equator the prevailing winds
are from the east, however in this part of the world prevailing
winds are from the west?
I mean, so clearly we're very, huh, clearly we're very geographically
located, right? This is not like everywhere in the world. Also what
about places that don't have an east to the city? Yeah, right.
In the spirit of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
Oh, you brought us something.
You brought Mardi Gras beads.
Great. The video is now working or otherwise I would definitely exhibit
them.
Yeah and this is more about the first chapter.
Is it a festival?
Well
actually,
well, okay with the King cake. Okay,
so basically what you're saying on the east and the western wind,
I'm sure you're familiar with the חמסין Chamsin winds in Israel, right?
They're like east winds. So there's different opinions why they're called חמסין,
Chamsin, if it's
חם Cham hot that comes from like סין Sin from the east,
but in Arabic חמסין Chamsin is fifty. So there's only no more
than fifty days like this in the year. So if you consider,
that would make it definitely that it's like whatever, a sixth, right?
Or less than a sixth of the year.
Yes, from three hundred and sixty-five.
And that's a cognate word to Hebrew.
And then right, and then it would be most of the time
it will be a western wind, so we can maybe understand it
from that. Okay.
אמר רב יוסף
Amar
Rav
Yosef but I bet you to track to the
outskirts of the city every time you have to. So I don't
know, look, I am very curious about this גמרא Gemara medicine. I
don't know if this is related directly to the sentence before it.
So when you're involved in this bloodletting, that might create more unusual
bathroom activity and therefore during those times do that. But some of
the instructions I'm not exactly sure how they connect to each other.
So I'll just leave it at this. Okay.
It sounds like you have to eat those specific foods.
And this would become a problem and that's why they had to
drink that and then make sure which direction.
Well, you're supposed to not eat those foods. Right, but if you
then this is the cure for it and then exactly, and then
be on that side because maybe that creates more of a bowel
movement.
Well, רב שרירא גאון Rav Sherira Gaon told us not to follow
this anyway.
Okay, so everything while we're on עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, בוקר טוב.
Boker Tov. אמר רב יהושע בן לוי מעלים אונקלי בשבת. Amar Rav
Yehoshua Ben Levi ma'alin unkli b'Shabbat. מאי אונקלי? Mai unkli? So we
can lift this אונקלי unkli thing on שבת. Shabbat. The
גמרא Gemara is asking, what is this אונקלי? unkli? אמר רב אבא
אסטומכא דליבא. Amar Rav Abba istumcha d'libba.
It's a, it's a bone that is near the heart on the
edge of the ribs and sometimes if it bends inwards, which I'm
not sure how we would know right at the top of כ"ט.
Kaf-Tet. Huh?
They perhaps suggest a muscle of the heart. Okay, but I don't
know, you know, it's various interpretations.
So yeah, this says it's a little bone that's near the heart
or near the ribs and it needs to be lifted and straightened
to the like back to the right place. מאי אסותא? Mai asuta?
What is the cure for somebody that this אונקלי unkli thing has
been bent? מיתי כמון כוייתא וניניא ואגדנא וצתרי ואבדתא. Meiti kammon k'vayata
v'ninya v'agadana v'tzatrei v'avadata.
So some of these are very similar to names we're commonly used,
right? כמון Kammon cumin,
caraway,
mint, נענע, Nana, אגדנא, Agadana,
I have wormwood, somebody has something else, צתרי Tzatrei something that's either
onion or garlic, ואבדתא V'avadata hyssop,
אזוב Ezov like the אזוב Ezov that's described in the תורה. Torah.
Okay. This is like and then the גמרא Gemara says this like
mixture of cumin, caraway,
נענע Nana etc. is good for, for several ailments. It
says לליבא בחמרא. L'libba b'chamra. If we want to cure heart things,
this above combination should be taken with חמרא chamra with wine. וסימנך,
V'simanach, how do we have a hint for it from the text?
ויין ישמח לבב אנוש. V'yayin yesamach levav enosh.
We are told that a wine will make a heart cheerful. Right?
This is in תהילים. Tehillim. So therefore
wine will cure the heart when it's mixed with this mixture. לרבחה
במיא. L'ruvcha b'maya. וסימנך V'simanach from בראשית, Bereishit, ורוח אלוהים מרחפת על
פני המים. V'ruach Elohim merachefet al pnei hamayim.
So רוח ruach has to do with מים. mayim. If we mix
this mixture with water, it will help diseases that are associated with
water like שחפת. shachefet. What is שחפת shachefet in
English?
Like a breathing fever kind of thing. Okay, I'll come
back to it. לחודא לחודא בשכרא
וסימנך
lachuda lachuda
b'shichara v'simanach and in בראשית Bereishis רבקה Rivka story, וכדה על
שכמה. v'kada al shichmah. כודא kuda is a woman who is giving
birth, who's sitting on the birthing stones and for her, mixing these
things with שכרא shichra with another kind
of a wine would be helpful. Huh?
Beer? Just beer.
Okay. Another kind of alcoholic drink.
Interesting maybe because beer is
made
of barley, right?
And they say because the first two letters of the שורש shoresh
are similar to to the word for beer שכרא. shichra.
Okay, so each one of these three is a פסוק pasuk that
somehow in the words of the פסוק pasuk hints to the situation.
The first one has heart and wine. We understand that those go
together. The second one has רוח ruach and water. So we understand
that water is good for like breathing...
Sorry, I'm blanking on this. And the third one has וכדה על
שכמה v'kada al shichmah and כדה kada the pitcher כד kad is
close to the word כודא kuda to the woman on the birthing
stones and שכרא shichra is close to שכמה shichmah her shoulders and
therefore we understand that those can help each other. רב אחא בריה
דרבא שחיק להו לכולהו בהדי הדדי ושקיל להו מלא חמש אצבעות ושתי
להו. Rav Acha brei d'Rava shachik lehu l'chulhu bahadi hadadei v'shakil lehu
mlo chamesh etzbaos v'shati lehu. So now we have different systems of
how do you take this. רב אחא Rav Acha the son of
רבא Rava would ground all of them together and take a handful
of this mixture, חמש אצבעות chamesh etzbaos like a full hand, and
drink it. רב אשי שחיק כל חד וחד לחודיה. Rav Ashi shachik
kol chad v'chad l'chudei. So רב אשי Rav Ashi would ground each
and every one of these herbs that we mentioned just earlier, the
cumin and the caraway and the ננא nana etc. and then ושקיל
מלא אצבעא רבתא ומלא אצבעא זוטרתי v'shakil mlo etzba rabasa u'mlo etzba
zutrasi and he would take them with like the thumb and the
little finger as opposed to the full hand. He would take just
like a little bit and use it this way. אמר רב פפא
אנא עבדי לכולהו הנך ולא איתסאי. Amar Rav Papa ana avdi l'chulhu
hanech v'lo itasai. I did all of this and I did not
get better. Strange. עד דאמר לי ההוא טייעא אייתי כוזא חדתא ומלייה
מיא
Ad d'amar li hahu taya ayisi
kuza chadasa u'malyei maya until I came across this non-Jew,
some people say an Ishmaelite, and he said to me, bring a
little cup of water, a little small cup, small container, fill it
up with water, ורמי ביה תרוודא דדובשא, v'rami bei tarvada d'duvsha,
put in this water a spoonful, big spoon of honey, דתלי ליה
בכוכבי, d'tali lei b'kochvei, that was under the sky or outdoors, leave
it outdoors, ולמחר אישתי, u'l'machar ishti, drink it the next day. עבדי
הכי ואיתסאי. avdi hachi v'itasai. I did this and I became well.
So I'm not sure what happens to water under the sky like
water outside but if it warms up it's almost like tea with
honey kind of thing, right? Like a hot water maybe if it
was outdoors, right? Because he says leave it to the next day.
Yes.
Just a couple of days ago we were talking we're not supposed
to drink water that's been left out overnight.
But this is for a healing. Also he says like nothing else
worked. I don't know.
I'm really not sure what to do with all this except that
I'm fascinated by it.
Maybe all the spices that's in it somehow chase away whatever the
demons are that are lurking.
Wait, the spices is what didn't work for him.
No, but when
you leave it out.
When you leave it out, the fact that it's got spices.
No, what he says is that
he's taking the water plain.
He's taking water with honey.
Well, I hate to tell you that water with honey is a
wonderful bacteria culture medium.
Yes, that's what I said like what happens to this thing when
it sits outside.
So the first two rabbis gave us the list of herbs, less
than spices, right? Cumin, ננא, nana, etc., and explained how they grind
it separately or together, take it one hand or take it like
this and eat it. And then רב פפא Rav Papa said, I
tried it, nothing worked for me, but this non-Jew said water and
honey, leave it overnight, and that helped me.
Look, we assume we know everything and they didn't know everything, but
I think we
don't know
everything.
Some of these things actually, some of the things that they mentioned
here, yes, actually are known to have some medicinal properties. Like what?
Like
some of the
some of the herbs they mention.
First, like, I mean,
people often advise people that are sick or have a cold or
whatever to have hot, I’ve heard, hot water, lemon and honey, like
no tea bag, just that.
Eating, drinking mint, cumin, cumin has become like a big thing with
whatever, turmeric, ginger, all these things.
If cumin and turmeric was what people said there’d be no disease
in India.
I eat cumin and turmeric all the time.
So
wait, but like what you’re saying right now is that disease only
comes from one thing. If you eat the right thing, you will
never be sick and if you don’t, you will always.
No, of course that’s not the case.
But it’s not true. Like there’s like whatever
hygiene and lots of other things. But cumin’s supposed to be good
for you. So.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. שישה דברים מרפאים את החולה מחליו ורפואתן
רפואה. Shisha devarim merapim et hacholeh mecholyov urefuatan refuah. So there’s six,
why did I say three, six things in foods that can cure
if a person is already sick, they can cure him from his
sickness
and
bring wellness, health. ואלו הן: Ve’elu hen: כרוב kruv ותרדין
vetardin ומי סיסין umei sissin יבשה, yeveshah, sorry,
וקיבת vekeivat והרת veharat ויותרת הכבד. veyotrat hakaved. ויש אומרים אף דגים
קטנים.
Veyesh omrim af
dagim ktanim. ולא עוד אלא שדגים קטנים מפרים ומרבים כל גופו של
אדם. Velo od ela shedagim ktanim mafrim umarbim kol gufo shel adam.
Okay, there’s six things that cure the sick person, and here they
are:
cabbage, I have תרדין tardin as beets.
That’s what I have.
Yeah, but our, you know, translations might out-talk each other. Like for
some reason it like makes me think of תרד tered like spinach.
But okay.
מי סיסין יבשה, Mei sissin yeveshah, water in which like chamomile was
soaked and then dried.
Chamomile’s an example of a medicinal good thing.
Yes.
קיבת, Keivat, stomach of an animal. הרת, Harat, a womb of a
small animal. ויותרת הכבד Veyotrat hakaved is a part of the liver.
And some say small fish also included in this list. And not
only that, but small fish, they like,
because fish has the quality or the symbolic quality of being fruitful,
then they like just make the whole person’s body happy, right, and
better.
עשרה דברים מחזירים את החולה לחליו וחליו קשה.
Asara devarim machzirim et hacholeh lecholyov
vecholyov kasheh. There’s ten things that make a person sick again and
make his illness even become worse. אלו הן. Elu hen. Tan tan
tan to all the vegetarians. האוכל בשר שור, Ha’ochel basar shor, שומן
בשר, צלי Shuman basar tzli, בשר, ציפורים, basar tziporin, ביצה צלויה, beitzah
tzluyah, שחלים. shachalim. שומן בשר צלי, Shuman basar tzli, בשר ציפורים, basar
tziporin.
ביצה צלויה, beitzah tzluyah, שחלים. shachalim.
שומן בשר shuman basar, צלי, בשר tzli basar, ציפורים.
tziporin, ושומן Veshuman comma בשר צלי. basar tzli.
Okay wait, I have to count the ten. בשר שור basar shor
is one, right?
Yeah. שומן shuman is the next thing.
בשר צלי, basar tzli, בשר ציפורים, basar tziporin, ביצה צלויה, beitzah tzluyah,
שחלים, shachalim, תגלחת, tiglachat, מרחץ, merchatz, גבינה, gevinah, וכבד. vechaved. ויש אומרים
אף אגוזים. Veyesh omrim af egozim.
ויש אומרים אף קישואים. Veyesh omrim af kishuim. Huh. So much for
that. Okay, let’s this...
אגוזים egozim are very good for you.
You
know, it’s like as soon as I present here, I feel like
I have to defend the גמרא. Gemara.
These sayings are for somebody who’s already ill, and there’s another saying,
you know, other words, these activities are considered overly taxing for a
weakened state. So digesting nuts might, nuts might be good for you,
maybe it’s hard to digest if you’re not well.
Right. So there’s also opinions that things that make you better when
you’re ill might make you ill when you’re well. Yes.
We laugh at this, but there’s a footnote that the רמבם Rambam
actually פוסקן paskens this way.
Yeah, yeah, I’m not I’m not...
look,
first,
I mean, a lot of people will swear by cleansing diets and...
Going vegan when you're whatever want to clean your
body of different things. Basically they tell us not to eat fat,
not to eat animal meat, not to eat bird meat, not to
eat eggs, not to eat cheese, not to eat liver, right?
Not to shave, not to bathe, which is, huh, what?
Liver can actually be good.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, we got into this earlier.
That a vegan diet could be shown to be healthy.
Vegan diets, yeah.
Again, depends, like people can get anemic and it can be bad
for them.
You may need to take a vitamin supplement.
I don't want to preach any given thing. I just want to
say that some of the stuff they're saying seems crazy to us,
some of the things we're doing would seem crazy to people in
other cultures and in other worlds.
And so I want to say look at it with like kind
of a little bit of curiosity. What did they know that we
don't know? Especially you say it went all the way to רמב"ם,
Rambam, right? So like some of this survived for hundreds of years
for some reason.
The interesting thing is that רמב"ם Rambam was after רב שרירא גאון
Rav Sherira Gaon who told us not to follow this.
Now does it have to do with culture? Does it have to
do with specific geographical areas? I don't know, we can't do all
this, don't do this.
I think רב שרירא גאון Rav Sherira Gaon said that we just
don't understand what a lot of these are and we don't understand
the science behind them and we should follow whatever the doctors say
in our time.
All right. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל: Tana dbei Rabi Yishmael: למה נקרא
שמן קישואין lama nikra sheman kishuin מפני שהן קשין mipnei shehen kashin
לכל גופו של אדם lechol gufo shel adam כחרבות. kacharavot. So
we're comparing the קישואין, kishuin,
the zucchinis or maybe this whole family of basically cucumbers. Cucumbers, but
maybe that for gardeners it's all the same family. These are just
large ones, the small ones are
okay they say.
So they are like swords, like big ones. All right. We're picking
up again, we've completed the medicine matters, sadly, and we're picking up
again from the last משנה. Mishnah. ואין מסתפרין מהן בכל מקום. vein
mistaprin mehen bechol makom. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: ישראל המסתפר מעובד כוכבים
רואה במראה Yisrael hamistaper me'oved kochavim ro'eh bamar'ah. ועובד כוכבים המסתפר מישראל
veoved kochavim hamistaper miYisrael כיון שהגיע לבלוריתו kivan shehigia levalarito שומט ידו.
shomeit yado. Okay.
So
this is somewhat contradictory or at least it's trying...
When I read that משנה Mishnah I could not help thinking about
Sweeney Todd.
About what?
Say more.
Sweeney Todd was a legendary barber who murdered his customers
and
served them to had a restaurant where he served them as meat
pies, and there's a Broadway show about it back in the 1970s.
All right, Charlie, this is R-rated.
This was in London? Yeah, it was in Broadway too, yeah.
No, I meant his story.
Yeah, he supposedly lived in London.
I think it's fascinating that they had mirrors, that mirror was a
thing, so in barber shops in barber shops, like that this whole
culture existed already so long ago. So first we say that one
may not have their haircut anywhere, right? And we'll see that the
rabbis try to deal with what is this anywhere, there was probably
a practical
where mirrors had everywhere anywhere.
חכמים Chachamim say רשות הרבים reshut harabim it's okay. Right, right, right,
coming.
Don't take the no, this is the משנה Mishnah we had before.
Right, תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Okay, we just read this. So the
ישראל, Yisrael, the Jew that has a haircut by an עובד כוכבים
oved kochavim should look at the gentile's or at the non-Jew's
at the עובד כוכבים's oved kochavim actions in the mirror when he
cuts his hair, which is interesting, but there's questions about it in
the commentators. Okay, so let's say you look in the mirror
and
then you see that he has a big knife and he's about
to cut your neck, what are you supposed to do about it?
Like, it's pretty late. Okay,
תוספות Tosafot is asking questions about it. Is it a matter of
שבת Shabbos looking in the mirror because you might pull a hair
that you see and he says the women saw that they have
white hair and so they pulled their white hairs out and they
shouldn't do this on שבת, Shabbos, which is also crazy. Like, clearly
vanity is something only of the 20th or 21st century, right? Not.
What exactly is the thing with the mirror? In the עובד כוכבים,
Oved Kochavim, if he gets a haircut by a Jew, then the
Jew should be mindful of the בלורית. blorit. בלורית, blorit, at least
in modern Hebrew, בלורית blorit is like this, the front of the
hair that has some
curl.
Others say it is the back of the hair, at least according
to Rashi, like this long braid, like a braid.
So I am biased because of the modern thing. It is like
songs about the guys of the פלמ"ח, Palmach, you know, early Israel,
that they had like a בלורית. blorit. They definitely did not have
a braid, but they had this thing that they could do.
Right. Okay. And so, like one should remove their hand, not cut
it, because this is related or associated with something that is idolatrous
practice.
אמר מר: Amar Mar: ישראל המסתפר מעובד כוכבים Yisrael hamistaper meoved kochavim
רואה במראה. roeh bamarah היכא דמי? Hecha dami? What is it that
we are talking about, this mirror business? אי ברשות הרבים למה לי
מראה? Ei bireshut harabim lama li mar'ah? Like if you are in
a public domain, why do you need a mirror? Because people will
see, like if somebody is chopping one's neck off, right, while barbering,
then there is going to be people there.
ואי ברשות היחיד כי רואה מראה הוי, Ve'ei bireshut hayachid ki ro'eh
mar'ah havi, how is it going to help him to see himself
in the mirror?
But the answer is לעולם ברשות היחיד וכיון דאיכא מראה מתחזי כאדם
חשוב. Lo'olam bireshut hayachid vecheivan de'ika mar'ah mitchazi ke'adam chashuv. So it
is very interesting, like this nuance. It is not that you can
do anything if you are sitting there with a mirror and you
are seeing something, but the understanding is that if you look behind
you, you must be a very important person that wants to see
what is going to happen around or is mindful of his surroundings,
and therefore the עובד כוכבים Oved Kochavim who is cutting the hair
is also going to be cautious with what they are doing and
not going to kill the person.
רב חנה בר ביזנא הוה מסתפר מעובד כוכבים בשבילי נהרדעא. Rav Chana
bar Bizna hava mistaper me'oved kochavim bishvilei Neharde'a.
So Rav Chana—so this—does this disagree with the teaching, basically, this teaching
about the mirror?
No, that in רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid you should have a מראה.
mar'ah.
Because
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
אין מסתפרים מהם בכל מקום. Ein mistaperim mehem bechol makom. Wait, wait,
come up.
Yes. And חכמים Hachamim say ברשות הרבים מותר Bireshut harabim mutar אבל
לא בינו לבינו. aval lo beino leveino.
Not רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid or not רשות הרבים? Reshut HaRabim?
They said the only place you can do it is רשות הרבים.
Reshut HaRabim. So here the גמרא Gemara is taking it, of course
you can do it in רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, you wouldn't even
need the mirror. So אבל לא בינו לבינו, Aval lo beino leveino,
unless it is saying but, oh, בינו לבינו beino leveino you can
if you have a mirror? So like whose is this teaching going
by? That is what I am trying to understand.
אבל לא בינו לבינו, Aval lo beino leveino, yeah, I see what
you are saying.
Or is it even going according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that
if you have a mirror that changes everything?
You'll see the little story.
I think, okay, so in the משנה Mishna it just says don't
get a haircut, right? And חכמים Hachamim say ברשות הרבים מותר Bireshut
harabim mutar אבל לא בינו לבינו.
aval lo
beino leveino.
And then does the גמרא Gemara add the fact that if you
have a mirror then you can? Does it make it רשות הרבים?
Reshut HaRabim? Right.
Is that going according to חכמים Hachamim that says בינו לבינו beino
leveino you can if you have a mirror? Or you know, but
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir still says no? Or is it רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says that if there is a mirror it is okay
everywhere? Or is this like totally different? You know, that's what I
am asking, I don't understand. I don't know either, what does—how does
that—what's the
הלכה, Halakha, right?
I mean,
today everyone goes to whichever barber, we're not really worried about anything.
Right.
But it's interesting, like you know what you're saying, like these Wild
West movies, right, when they're shaving and they have some serious conversation
and they go like, 'Hmm, so about that.' Okay, רב חנה בר
ביזנא, Rav Chana bar Bizna, so he tells a story that he
goes in the שבילים shvilim of נהרדעא, Neharde'a, so he's
not—it's—you'll see in a minute, it's unclear where exactly he is. Is
he in the city or is he in the outskirts? Is it
רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim or רשות היחיד? Reshut HaYachid? And he but
he goes to have his haircut with an עובד כוכבים. Oved Kochavim.
אמר לו: חנה חנה יאי קואיך לזוגא. Amar lo: Chana Chana ya'e
kavayich lezuga. He says to him, 'Chana, Chana, your neck is so
beautiful next to my
scissors.' אמר: תיתי לי דעברי אהא דרבי מאיר. Amar: Titi li de'avarei
ada deRabbi Meir. This is what I get for transgressing on what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said, not to have a haircut even in
רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim with the עובד כוכבים. Oved Kochavim. And what
he meant, I think, because he survives this, it's not like he
dies then,
I should have heard the end of this. Just that fear, that
fright, of like right now I'm in the hands of this guy
with the knife, that fear, like I deserve it because I did
not listen to the words of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir*.
I really love that moment because think about it, like for רב
Rav חנה *Rav Chana*, his fear is a direct result of his
actions.
It's not a direct result of the non-Jew being unsafe or whatever,
like it's like, oh, this is because I did not listen to
רבי Rabbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir*.
Which is what they tell kids, right? You scare them, don't do
whatever, and now all of a sudden they're scared of it when
maybe they wouldn't have been before.
Yeah, and like some things are good to be scared of, and
some things yes.
So that they learn fear is not bad.
Yes. But he immediately connects his actions with not listening to רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, right? Not with, oh yeah, we always knew the
עכום *Akum* are dangerous, right? Or blah blah blah. Okay. והרבנן
לא עבר *V'darabbanan lo avar*, this is exactly what Michael brought up.
Like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* said בכל מקום *b'chol makom* and רבנן
*Rabbanan* also said not to go to have a haircut. Now the
question is: is it רשות הרבים *reshuth harabim* or רשות היחיד *reshuth
hayachid*? אימר דאמור רבנן ברשות הרבים וברשות היחיד
מי אמר *Imar d'amur Rabbanan b'reshuth harabim u'v'reshuth hayachid mi amar*? Who
said that in רשות היחיד *reshuth hayachid* it's okay to have a
haircut by like be alone with a knife with somebody that you're
not sure you can trust? והוא סבר שבילי דנהרדעא כיון דשכיחי רבים
כרשות הרבים דמו *V'hu savar shvilei d'naharda'a keivan d'shchichi rabim k'reshuth harabim
damu*. So from that we understand, he thought, let me finish the
translation and then explain, רב Rav חנה
*Rav Chana* thought that the side streets of נהרדעא *Neharde'a*, since there's
many people present in it, they are like a public domain and
not a private domain. So he went there thinking it's a public
domain. Therefore we can understand that the ruling eventually for רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* it was nowhere, but for the חכמים *Chachamim* it was
in רשות הרבים *reshuth harabim* okay, and in רשות היחיד *reshuth hayachid*
no. Long תוספות *Tosafot* on it if you in your free time
want to look at it, המסתפר *Hamistaper* on left side because I
think תוספות *Tosafot* is dealing with the fact that people eventually do
go to have a haircut with somebody non-Jewish. And at the end
he says if you have someone else with you, then it's okay
because you're like not going to be alone. Okay. ועובד כוכבים המסתפר
מישראל כיון שהגיע לבלוריתו שומט ידו *V'oved kochavim hamistaper mi-Yisrael keivan she-higia
l'vlorito shomet yad*. The עובד כוכבים *oved kochavim* that has his haircut
cut by a Jew, by ישראל *Yisrael*, when the barber
reaches the בלורית *blorit*, then he removes his hand and does not
cut it because this is associated with idolatrous practices. וכמה *V'chama*? How
much closer should we get to it? אמר רב מלכיא Rav Malkia
אמר רב Rav. אדא בר אהבה שלוש אצבעות לכל רוח ורוח *Amar
Rav Malkia amar Rav Adda bar Ahava shalosh etzba'ot l'chol ruach v'ruach*.
So this is like stay away three fingers breadth in every direction.
Slight digression because this is a quote that's being said by רב
מלכיא Rav Malkia. *Rav Malkia* and we will see a very quick
discussion we should not fall into. אמר רב חנינא בריה דרב איקא
שפוד שפחות shfachot, וגומות רב מלכיו Rav Malkio. בלורית אפר מקלה וגבינה
רב מלכיא Rav Malkia, *Amar Rav Chanina brei d'Rav Ika shapud shfachot
v'gumot Rav Malkiyo blorit efer miklah v'gvina Rav Malkia*. So they're like
questioning who said this statement about the three fingers breadth. We have
two rabbis with very similar names, one is called רב מלכיא Rav
Malkia *Rav Malkia* and one is called רב מלכיו Rav Malkio *Rav
Malkiyo*. רב מלכיו *Rav Malkiyo* has three rulings that are specific to
him. One is the שפוד *shapud*, it's a skewer that whether we
can leave it on the fire or not. One is the
שפחות *shfachot*,
that when a woman has maidservants she should still keep busy and
not do nothing because doing nothing leads to trouble. And גומות *gumot*,
גומות *gumot* are like
dimples in the skin that if you see a hair in them
in the one, it defines a girl or somebody's age. Okay, those
are by רב מלכיו *Rav Malkiyo*. בלורית *blorit*, which we see here,
the hair thing, אפר *efer*, burnt ashes, and cheese, we'll talk about
cheese in a minute. Those are rulings by רב *Rav* רב מלכיא.
Rav Malkia אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa
has a different way to remember who said
what: מתניתי Matniti ומתניתא u-Matnita רב מלכיא Rav Malkia because they sound
kind of the same. שמעתתא Shematata רב מלכיו. I don't know why
he decides this, but because מתניתא Matnita and מלכתא Malkata and מלכיא
Malkia sounds like a feminine form of the word, and מלכתא Malkata
and מתניתא Matnita sound like feminine, so those are the statements by
רב מלכיא. Malkia, מאי בינייהו, Mai beinaiahu, what is the difference? איכא
בינייהו Ika beinaiahu שפחות, the ruling of the fact that when a
woman has maids and she should still keep busy, that is something
that is a dispute between them. Okay. Question.
רב מלכיו is not a common,
right, not a common name אמורא. Amora.
Is he in בבל Bavel or in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, do
you know?
I don't know. פפא Pappa is in the בבל, Bavel, so maybe
they're talking about the other בבלי. Bavli.
In Roman society, from our perspective, maybe not from Roman perspective, there
were a lot of well-off, well-educated women who were completely excluded from
any role in anything,
and the level of licentiousness,
Jews or not Jews?
These are non-Jewish women. Yeah. And these, and the level of licentiousness
in that society, particularly under the—in the upper classes was unbelievable. And
they might have been this—some of the references
in the משנה Mishnah could be related to this aspect
of Roman society.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay.
משנה Mishnah top of כ"ט עמוד ב'. Kaf-tet Amud Bet. מתניטין. Matnitin.
We have a long משנה Mishnah in front of us, we are
probably
not going to be able to unpack everything but hopefully at least
understand what's ahead of us in the גמרא Gemara of the coming
days. Yes. You can always ask. You can always ask. Yeah.
So the term רב and the other's רבי here, you said רב
מלכיא, could that be a indication of where they're located? Back at
the top?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
רב מלכיא as opposed
to—so how in the English it's translated, it says רב for מלכיא,
it looks like maybe it's—oh, it's רב מלכיא also. Okay.
Yeah, I'm not—they're both
רב. רב מלכיא ורב מלכיו.
ve-Rav Malkio. Thank you.
I'm not sure that we should sit there, but I don't know
if I can add any more. Okay.
משנה: Mishnah: אלו דברים של עובדי
כוכבים אסורים ואיסורן
איסור הנאה.
Elu devarim shel ovdei kochavim asurim
ve-isuran isur hana'ah.
So here are things that the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim are doing
or having that are forbidden on us, and the איסור issur is
איסור הנאה, isur hana'ah, we can't even derive any pleasure from it.
It's important because it's like the משנה Mishnah switches. Up until now,
we dealt with things that are סכנה, sakanah, things that are—that there
is dangers,
whether it was עריות arayot or רביעיה, revi'iah, and now we're moving
to things that are more about us not mixing in, avoiding opportunities
that might not cause a life danger but are preventing us from
mixing. היין, Ha-yayin, and we will have a discussion about the יין
נסך, yayin nesech, והחומץ ve-ha-chometz של עובדי כוכבים shel ovdei kochavim שהיה
מתחילתו יין. she-haya mi-tchilato yayin.
So wine, vinegar of the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim that from the
get-go used to be wine,
וחרס אדריאני, ve-cheres Adriani, I'll read—I'll explain in just a second, ועורות
לבובין. ve-orot levuvin. רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel says,
אומר, omer, בזמן שהקרע שלו עגול אסור משוך מותר. bi-zman she-ha-kera she-lo
agol asur mashuch mutar. Okay.
So wine kind of obvious. Vinegar that was—used to be wine and
became sour, became vinegar, also prohibited. חרס אדריאני, Cheres Adriani, very fascinating.
This is clay that was not baked, okay, so therefore it was
still soft and it was soaked in wine. So it was like
wine concentrate, right?
Like Kool-Aid wine in clay.
And this was something from the Hadrianic period or maybe Hadrian himself,
he would make כלי חרס, kli cheres, vessels like this, soak them
in wine, not bake them, they become a traveling wine that you
could take with you. You could take broken shards of this clay,
put it in water, the wine will come out, mix it, right?
Because it's not baked, the חרס cheres will sink to the bottom
and you'll have a drink that's wine.
So the חרס הדריאני cheres Adriani might look just like a vessel,
but really it is soaked in wine that we should not be
eating. עורות לבובין orot levuvin are leathers that have a hide, I
guess, that have a tear opposite the heart, and this was indicative
of idolatrous practices because they would like cut the leather,
the skin of the animal, and pull the heart out. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says, I
was not going to go into this.
Oh, but the Aztecs did that to people.
Thank you. Thank you, Charlie.
Live from Riverdale! You know, a lot of these practices really did
happen.
Yes. Yeah, this is they were not making this stuff up.
No, I don't think they were making this stuff up.
How from a certain perspective, this idea of wanting to have a
sense of the life force, you
know, people eat brains, right?
Because they think this right out of a live, yeah, out of
a live like monkey or something. I mean, that's yeah, I think
they do.
All right, all right,
all right.
This
is a big one. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says you can tell if it was done for basically he says
to us, you can tell if it was done for idolatry or
not. If the tear is round, that means it was used for
idolatrous practices to remove the heart, therefore אסור. assur. But if it's
משוך, mashuch, if it's like a long tear, then maybe whatever, it
was just a hide of an animal and it's not not used
for sacrifice.
Okay.
בשר הנכנס לעבודת כוכבים מותר והיוצא אסור מפני שהוא
כזבחי מתים דברי רבי עקיבא.
Basar hanichnas l'avodat kochavim mutar vehayotzei assur mipnei shehu
kezivchei meitim divrei Rabbi Akiva.
Meat that is entering the house of idolatry is permitted, and meat
that exits is forbidden because it is considered that it was already
been part of the offering to the dead, and this is to
the idols, the זבחי מתים, zivchei meitim, and this is a statement
of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. I have questions about it and I'm
not sure I can answer myself because
it
would be surprising to me that meat even that is entering is
allowed, is permitted.
Okay, hopefully the גמרא Gemara will unpack it later. ההולכים לתרפות אסור
לשאת ולתת עמהם והבאים מותרים. Haholchim letarpot assur laset velatet imahem vehaba'im
mutarim.
People that go to this either it's a festival of idolatry, תרפות,
tarpot,
we can't I'll explain we can't engage with them when they're going
there because the understanding is that us having commerce with them they
will either be thankful for their idols and use our... Huh?
Or use the money.
Use the money.
I just got back from Mardi Gras.
See, but if you come back, then we can do business with
you and we can study דף daf with you and it says
what is תרפות? tarpot? Two possibilities.
One is the תרפים, teraphim, like in the story of רחל, Rachel,
that these are right idols and therefore the festival of house of
idols. Another thing is that it's בית התורפה Beit haturpah is a
nice name for sexual organs and therefore it's
another
kind of place. All right. נודות עובדי כוכבים וקנקניהן ויין של ישראל
כנוס בהן אסורין ואיסורן איסור הנאה דברי רבי מאיר.
Nodot ovdei chochavim vekankaneihen veyayin shel Yisrael kanus
bahen assurim ve'issuran issur hana'ah divrei Rabbi Meir.
נודות Nodot is a flask I think that's made out of
leather, okay, still used today. וקנקניהן Vekankaneihen is made out of חרס,
cheres, out of clay. ויין של ישראל כנוס בהן, Veyayin shel Yisrael
kanus bahen, if the wine of the Jew is in them, they're
forbidden and it's an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah according to רבי מאיר.
וחכמים אומרים אין איסורן איסור הנאה. Vachachamim omrim ein issuran issur hana'ah.
It's not a איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. החרצנים והזגין של עובדי כוכבים
אסורין ואיסורן איסור הנאה דברי רבי מאיר וחכמים אומרים לחים
אסורין יבשים מותרים.
Hachartzanim vehazagin shel ovdei chochavim assurim ve'issuran issur hana'ah divrei Rabbi
Meir vachachamim omrim lachim assurim yeveshim mutarim. Okay, החרצנים hachartzanim are the
seeds, וזגין vezagin are the peel of the grapes. So this is
byproducts of making wine of the
עובדי כוכבים. ovdei chochavim. if they're
if they're still wet, if they're still like in process and I
think it's Rashi that says 12 months will be considered in this
state of לחים, lachim, then they're forbidden, but if they're יבשים, yevashim,
if they're dry, then they are מותרים, mutarim, then they're permissible. המורייס
וגבינת בית אונייקי של עובדי כוכבים אסורים, ואיסורן איסור הנאה, דברי רבי
מאיר. וחכמים אומרים: אין איסורם איסור הנאה. Hamorais vegvinat beit unaiki shel
ovdei kochavim asurim, ve-isuran issur hana'ah, divrei Rabbi Meir. Ve-chachamim omrim: ein
isuram issur hana'ah. מורייס Morais is a small fish and גבינת בית
אונייקי Gevinat Beit Unaiki I actually went and looked at the בית
אונייקי Beit Unaiki place. This is
there's going to be more discussion about it later in עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. It's supposedly a state, place, city in northwestern Asia
Minor, is that how you say it? Yes. Like where Turkey is
today and they were one of the things that they were famous
about is that they would make cheese with wine from idolatrous practices.
So they were known to be a not reliable place for cheese.
Also very interesting and since we're coming up on cheese business,
apparently, I did not know this before preparing for this משנה, mishnah,
so I found this very interesting:
it's not possible to make cheese from a non-kosher
animal
from a בהמה טמאה, behemah teme'ah, like there's no camel cheese. But
there's cheeses so much so that once upon a time
people would buy butter, like butter would be okay to purchase, I'm
not telling you to purchase butter חס וחלילה chas ve-chalilah without all
the right הכשרים, hechsherim, but once upon a time people would do
it because you could only make butter from animals that were permitted
to eat and the process was straightforward, just let the fat rise
and sit. The cheese is a problem, we'll see coming up, yes.
To this day in the United States it is illegal to sell
dairy products across state lines when the product is from anything other
than a goat, sheep, or cow.
Okay.
Is that the influence of the Jewish population?
It's an interesting question, there's actually an organized effort to legalize interstate
sale of camel milk.
But but camel milk or pig milk? So milk has issues.
Different than cheese.
Milk has to be kosher if it has no additives, but all
milk has additives so it needs a הכשר. hechsher.
But the fact that butter can only be made from בהמה טהורה
behemah tehorah and also cheese.
Actually this is not, I realized this isn't completely true. There's a
chef in Brooklyn who actually whose wife had a baby and he
made cheese out of his mother out of his wife's breast milk.
All right. We wanted to know
this. Now the question that's coming up for us in the משנה
mishnah is what kind of enzymes did he put it in? All
right, so here we come. Okay, so אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi
Yehuda, שאל רבי ישמעאל. sha'al Rabbi Yishmael. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
tells us about a conversation between רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי
יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. שאל רבי ישמעאל את רבי יהושע כשהיו מהלכין בדרך.
Sha'al Rabbi Yishmael et Rabbi Yehoshua k'shehayu mahalchin baderech.
I don't know why that detail is important to us. מפני מה
אסרו גבינות עובדי כוכבים? mipnei mah asru gevinot ovdei kochavim? Why are
they forbidding to us the cheeses of the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim
if cheese can only be made from kosher animals, what is the
what is the problem?
And he said, אמר לו מפני שמעמידין אותה בקיבה של נבלה. amar
lo mipnei shema'amidin otah bekeivah shel nevelah. Why would they put the
cheese in the stomach of a נבלה? nevelah? Because this is the
process that we still have today. We have to question what kind
of enzymes go into the cheese in order to cheesify it, right,
in order לגבן legaben it. And in those days, they would take
a stomach of a dead animal, use it to put the milk
in it and it would become cheese. אמר לו והלא קיבת עולה
חמורה מקיבת נבלה. amar lo vehalo keivat olah chamurah mikeivat nevelah. So
now we have a question:
which is worse? Can we use a stomach of an animal that
is being brought up as an עולה, olah,
or is that better or worse than the קיבה keivah of the
נבלה, nevelah, of an animal that just died?
אמרו כהן שדעתו יפה שורפה חיה ולא הודו לו, אבל אמרו אין
נהנין ולא מועלין. Amru kohen sheda'ato yafah sorfah chayah velo hodu lo,
aval amru ein nehenin velo mo'alin. So a כהן *kohen* who
I like this שדעתו יפה *sheda'ato yafa* who is open minded, he's
not an istinist, then he may eat the
stomach content
while they're still raw, right? And the Sages did not agree with
him, but the fact is that it was done.
I
have
to teach this sitting; it makes me nauseous.
But the Sages said אין נהנים ולא מועלים *ein nehenim v'lo moalim*.
Like with עולה *ola* you have an added problem because it might
be מעילה *meila*, like it might be that you're misusing something that's
supposed to be for a sacrifice. So deriving benefit from the stomach
content of the עולה *ola* we might think is
a problem, but it's really not forbidden by Torah law. So you
could you could do this.
So now we're asking a question. The עולה *ola* has against it
הנאה *hana'ah* and מעילה *meila* and the נבלה *neveila* only is איסור
אכילה *issur achila*, only is not allowed to eat.
So what is the problem with that cheese with the
earlier
discussion? אמר לו *amar lo* מפני שמעמידין אותה בקיבת עגלי עבודת כוכבים
*mipnei shema'amidin otah bekeivat eglei avodat kochavim*. Really the problem is that
they put it in the stomach of עגלים *agalim*, of calves that
were intended or are being used for idolatrous practices.
And since we have like you know we have a prohibition to
enjoy them, then the cheese that has been cheesified, that has been
made into a cheese inside the stomach is also forbidden. אמר לו
*amar lo* אם כן למה לא אסרוה בהנאה *im ken lama lo
asaruha behana'ah*? רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* said to him, if so, then
why didn't the Sages also forbid deriving any benefit from this cheese
instead of just forbidding only the consumption, only eating it, but also
they should have derived the benefit. So רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* didn't
answer him. השיאו לדבר אחר *he'si'o ledavar acher*. He's like let's talk
about something else. אמר לו *amar lo* ישמעאל *Yishmael* היאך אתה קורא
*ha'ech attah korei* כי טובים דודיך מיין *ki tovim dodecha miyayin* או
*o* כי טובים דודייך *ki tovim doda'ich*? He takes him on a
tangent into the Song of Songs.
He takes him on a tangent into the Song of Songs and
he says how do you read this פסוק *pasuk*? Do you read
it כי טובים דודיך *ki tovim dodecha* in the male, or כי
טובים דודייך *ki tovim doda'ich* or in the female, in the feminine
form? רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* says אמר לו *amar lo* כי טובים
דודייך *ki tovim doda'ich*. אמר לו *amar lo* אין הדבר כן *ein
hadavar ken* שהרי חבירו מלמד עליו *sheharei chavero melamed alav* לריח שמניך
טובים *lerach shemanecha tovim*. The next פסוק *pasuk* is in the masculine;
it says לריח שמניך *lerach shemanecha*,
for your oils in the masculine, and therefore דודיך *dodecha* should also
be in the masculine and we'll see later on, hopefully the גמרא
*Gemara* will unpack it. גמרא *Gemara* is asking us יין מנלן yayin
minalan *yayin minalan*? And it's it's interesting because we do not have
we want to find a פסוק *pasuk* for יין נסך *yayin nesech*.
So why do we need a פסוק *pasuk*? Because anything used in
idolatrous practice is אסור *assur*. Why do we need a special why?
This is the question of the גמרא *Gemara*. We're trying to find
out is it a גזירה *gezeira* that is derived from the Rabbis,
or is it something that is על פניו *al panav*, you know,
obviously there? אמר רבא בר אבוה *amar Rava bar Avuha* אמר קרא
*amar kra*, things in Deuteronomy 32, it says אשר חלב זבחימו יאכלו
ישתו יין נסיכם *asher chelev zevacheimo yocheilu yishtu yein nesichem*. So the
פסוק *pasuk* said those who eat the חלב *chelev*, sorry, the fat
of their offerings, the חלב *chelev* of their זבחים *zvachim*, and drink
the wine of their drink offerings, right, of the נסך *nesech*. So
now this verse juxtaposes the sacrifice, the זבח *zevach* with the wine,
with the wine, sorry. And we will see, and I think I
have to wrap with this by my time here, that we will
see that in the next few paragraph the גמרא *Gemara* is going
to juxtapose different פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* in order to come back to
the wine. And basically will say if the זבח *zevach* is like
wine, and if the זבח *zevach* is like dead, and if the
dead is we're not allowed to derive benefit from the dead and.
and we find that out because we juxtapose the עגלה ערופה and
מרים Miriam and they all have to do with קדשים Kodshim then
we derive from that set of פסוקים how we are the יין
מנלן piece, where do we get from that we can't use the
wine. I will stop with this
and wishing everybody a good day, don't try all those foods all
at once.
Thank you.